Speier, Hans; Papers ger084
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Hans Speier Papers1922-1989
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Speier, Hans
ger084
16.5 cubic ft.
The Hans Speier Papers primarily focus on Speier's career in the U.S. after his emigration. The collection includes correspondence with colleagues and leading scholars of the day, including Max Ascoli, Reinhard Bendix, Arvid Brodersen, Lewis A. Coser, Alexander George, Herbert Goldhammer, Joseph Goldsen, Fred C. Iklé, Alvin Johnson, Paul Kecskemeti, Henry J. Kellermann, Ernst Kris, Nathan Leites, M. Rainer Lepsius, Hans Staudinger and Leo Strauss. Also represented in the collection is a lengthy correspondence with co-editors of Propaganda and Communication in World History, Harold Lasswell and Daniel Lerner, and individual contributors. The RAND Corporation materials document Speier's career as organizer and Head of the Social Science Division of the RAND Corporation and a member of the RAND Research Council. During those years he wrote and directed numerous studies for RAND and the texts of many of the position papers, memoranda, lecture texts and essays are present in the collection. Included in the Nazi and anti-Nazi propaganda materials is a collection of rare leaflets prepared by the Psychological Warfare Branch of the U.S. Army and disseminated to enemy troops in Italy in 1943-1944. The collection also contains numerous texts of essays, as well as typescript and manuscript versions of books.
Biographical Sketch
During his lifetime Hans Speier was distinguished by two very distinct careers. Speier was a lecturer in political sociology and economics in Germany (1931-1933) before emigrating to the U.S. to accept a position as lecturer and professor of political sociology on the newly formed Graduate Faculty of the New School for Social Research in New York (1933-1942, 1947-1948), lecturing summers at the University of Illinois (1941) and the University of Michigan (1941). Speier interrupted his university career for one in government service and research, but returned to teaching in 1969 at the University of Massachusetts, Amherst (1969-1973), where he held the title of Robert M. MacIver Professor of Sociology and Government.
Between 1942 and 1948, Speier served in the Foreign Broadcast Intelligence Service of the Federal Communications Commission (later Chief of the Central European Section), advisor on propaganda policy to the Director of the Overseas Branch, Office of War Information, and eventually became Associate Chief of the State Department's Occupied Areas Division. In 1948, Speier joined the staff of The Rand Corporation in Santa Monica, California, first serving as the Organizer and Head of the Social Science Division from 1948 to 1960, later becoming a member of the Rand Research Council from 1960-1968.
Speier's research interests focus on the political implications of military affairs and the influence of military power on the behavior of governments in the conduct of his foreign policies. He authored or co-edited numerous books and articles on these subjects, including German Radio Propaganda (with Ernst Kris, 1944), Social Order and the Risks of War (1952), West German Leadership and Foreign Policy (with W. Davison, 1957), German Rearmament and Atomic War (1957), Divided Berlin: The Anatomy of Soviet Political Blackmail (1961), Die Angestellten vor dem Nationalsozialismus (1977; English title: German White Collar Workers and the Rise of Hitler), and Propaganda and Communication in World History (co-edited with Harold Lasswell and Daniel Lerner, 3 vols., 1979-1980). He also published his translation of Grimmelshausen's Courage, the Adventuress and the False Messiah (1964), as well his autobiographical account, From the Ashes of Disgrace: A Journal from Germany 1945-1955 (1981).
Speier was married twice, first in 1929 to Lisa (Luise) Griesbach, with whom he had two children, Sybil D. and Steven W. Lisa Speier died in 1965 and Speier married his second wife Margit in February 1967. Hans Speier, the last surviving member of the famed Graduate Faculty of the New School for Social Research, died at the age of 85 on February 17, 1990 while vacationing in Sarasota, Florida.
Chronology of Events:
1905 Born on February 3 in Berlin, Germany; son of Adolf and Anna Person Speier.
1923-1928 Studied Economics, Modern History and Sociology at the Universities of Berlin and Heidelberg.
1928 Received Dr. Phil. degree from the University of Heidelberg, where he was the assistant to Professor Emil Lederer.
1928-1930 Social Science editor at Ullstein Publishing House, Berlin.
1929 August 30, married Lisa (Luise) Griesbach (two children, Sybil D. and Steven W.)
1931-1933 Lecturer in Political Sociology at the College for Politics (Hochschule für Politik), Berlin and Assistant in the Department of Economics, University of Berlin. Editor of the Archiv für Sozialwissenschaft und Sozialpolitik.
1933 September, emigrated to the U.S.
1933-1942 Professor of Sociology, Graduate Faculty, New School for Social Research, New York.
1936 (Summer) Visiting Professor, University of Illinois. Publication of The Salaried Employee in German Society in mimeographed form by Columbia University as WPA project (a work begun by Speier in 1932 and eventually published in its entirety over 40 years later as Die Angestellten vor dem Nationalsozialismus).
1939 Co-edited and co-authored War in Our Time with Alfred Kahler
1940 April 20, became naturalized U.S. citizen.
1941 (Summer) Visiting Professor, University of Michigan.
1941-1942 Co-Director of Research Project on Totalitarian Communication, which was financed for two years by the Rockefeller Foundation for training of Rockefeller Research Fellows and study of classified British materials (monitored German broadcasts and British foreign broadcast analyses).
1942-1944 Section Chief and later Acting Chief of Foreign Broadcast Intelligence Service in the Federal Communications Commission, Washington, D.C.
1944 Co-authored with Ernst Kris German Radio Propaganda
1944-1945 Propaganda Policy Adviser to the Chief of the Overseas Branch of the Office of War Information, Washington, D.C.
1945 October 13 - December 2, trip to Germany for Office of War Information.
January 1946-September 1947 Associate Chief (Acting Chief) of Division for Occupied Areas (ADO) in the Department of State.
1946 February 9 - March 20, trip to Germany for Department of State.
1947 March - April, trip to Germany for Department of State.
1947-1948 Professor of Sociology, Graduate Faculty, New School for Social Research, New York.
1948 March - April, trip to Germany for Department of State.
1948-1960 Organizer and Head, Social Science Division, The Rand Corporation.
1947-1951 Consultant, Department of State
1950 October 31 - December 2, trip to Germany as Consultant for the Department of State.
1951 Consultant, Ford Foundation.
1952 April - June, trip to Germany for Rand to study conditions. Publication of Social Order and The Risks of War (re-issued by M.I.T. Press in 1969).
1954 March - June, trip to Germany for Rand to study conditions.
1955 September - November, trip to Germany for Rand to study conditions.
1956-1957 On leave from Rand; Fellow at the Center for Advanced Study in the Behavioral Sciences, Stanford University.
1957 Publication of German Rearmament and Atomic War; co-editor with W. P. Davison of West German Leadership and Foreign Policy.
1958-1962 Consultant, USAF Scientific Advisory Board
1960-1968 Member of the Rand Research Council; Chairman from 1961-1962.
1961 Publication of Divided Berlin: The Anatomy of Soviet Political Blackmail.
1964 On leave from Rand; Senior Fellow at the Council on Foreign Relations, New York. Publication of his translation of Grimmelshausen's Courage, the Adventuress and the False Messiah.
1965 December 21, Death of first wife, Lisa.
1967 February 18, married second wife, Margit Leipnik.
1969-1973 Professor at the University of Massachusetts, Amherst.
1969 Publication of Force and Folly: Essays on Foreign Affairs and the History of Ideas.
1975 Publication of Witz und Politik: Essay über das Lachen und die Macht.
1977 Publication of Die Angestellten vor dem Nationalsozialismus.
1979-1980 Co-editor with Harold Lasswell and Daniel Lerner of 3-volume publication Propaganda and Communication in World History.
1981 Published his autobiographical essay, From the Ashes of Disgrace: A Journal from Germany, 1945-1955.
1990 Died on February 17 while vacationing in Sarasota, Florida.
Scope and Contents
The Hans Speier Papers, 1922-1989, primarily focus on Speier's career in the United States after his emigration to the United States in 1933. A small number of documents for both Speier and his wife, Lisa Griesbach Speier, date from the pre-U.S. period, 1922-1933. Early materials are in German, with post-1933 materials predominately in English.
The collection is divided into ten series: 1) Biographical materials, including family documents and correspondence, 1922-1984; 2) Autobiographical writings, 1945-1989; 3) Correspondence files, 1911-1988; 4) Manuscripts and typescripts, ca. 1920-1987; 5) The RAND Corporation materials, 1948-1988; Miscellaneous typescripts by other authors, 1941-1982; 6) Miscellaneous typescripts by other authors, 1941-1982; 7) Nazi propaganda, 1941-1944; Anti-Nazi propaganda, 1943-1944; Allied Forces Intelligence Reports and memoranda, 1940-1948; 8) Notes and materials on various topics; and 9) Note cards;and 10) Political pamphlets, 1934-1970. Series 4 is further divided into two sub-series: typescripts of books written or edited by Speier, and typescripts of shorter writings, including poetry, short stories and essayistic writings. Series 5 is also divided into two sub-series: Hans Speier's log notes (diary entries) and the essayistic writings.
The correspondence files contain correspondence with colleagues and leading scholars of the day, including Max Ascoli, Reinhard Bendix, Arvid Brodersen, Lewis A. Coser, Alexander George, Herbert Goldhamer, Joseph Goldsen, Fred C. Iklé, Alvin Johnson, Paul Kecskemeti, Henry J. Kellermann, Ernst Kris, Nathan Leites, M. Rainer Lepsius, Hans Staudinger and Leo Strauss. Also represented in the collection is a lengthy correspondence with co-editors of the three-volume work Propaganda and Communication in World History Harold Lasswell and Daniel Lerner, as well as correspondence with individual contributors to the volumes.
Two additional series should be noted: The RAND Corporation materials (Series 5) and the Nazi propaganda and anti-Nazi propaganda and intelligence materials (Series 7). The RAND Corporation materials span four decades and document Speier's important career as organizer and Head of the Social Science Division of the RAND Corporation from 1948-1960 and a member of the RAND Research Council from 1960-1968. During those years he wrote and directed numerous studies for RAND and the texts of many of the position papers, memoranda, lecture texts and essays are present in the collection. Included in the Nazi and anti-Nazi propaganda materials is a collection of rare leaflets prepared by the Psychological Warfare Branch of the U.S. Army and disseminated to enemy troops in Italy in 1943-1944.
In addition to the numerous texts written by Speier during his years at The RAND Corporation, the collection also contains numerous texts of essays, as well as typescript and manuscript versions of books, in particular the monograph Die Angestellten vor dem Nationalsozialismus (1977) and his autobiographical work From the Ashes of Disgrace: A Journal from Germany, 1945-1955.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is organized as follows:
Acquisition Information
All items in this manuscript group were donated to the University Libraries, M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives, by Hans Speier in 1988.
Access
Access to this record group is unrestricted.
Public Servants; Political Science; Military and Armed Conflict; Germans -- United States.; Sociologists -- United States.; Sociologists -- Germany.; World War, 1939-1945 -- Propaganda.; World War, 1939-1945 -- Psychological aspects.; World War, 1939-1945 -- Campaigns.; World War, 1939-1945 -- German Americans.; Psychological warfare.; Propaganda, German.; Propaganda, Anti-German.; Propaganda, American.; Germany -- Politics and government -- 1945-1990.; Speier, Hans.; Ascoli, Max, 1898-1978.; Bendix, Reinhard.; Brodersen, Arvid, 1904-1996.; Coser, Lewis A., 1913-2003.; Goldhammer, Herbert.; Goldsen, Joseph M.; Iklé, Fred Charles.; Johnson, Alvin.; Kecskemeti, Paul.; Kellermann, Henry J.; Kris, Ernst, 1900-1957.; Lasswell, Harold D. (Harold Dwight), 1902-1978.; Leites, Nathan, 1912-1987.; Lepsius, Richard, 1810-1884.; Lerner, Daniel.; Staudinger, Hans, 1889-1980.; Strauss, Leo.; New School for Social Research (New York, N.Y.: 1919-1997); Rand Corporation. Social Sciences Division.
- Biographical materials, 1922-1984; 1; 29 file folders
  Scope and Contents
  The materials in this series pertain primarily to Hans Speier, and his first wife Lisa (Luise) Griesbach Speier and include school and university certificates for both from Germany. Also included in the series is correspondence with family members, including the Speier children, Sybil and Steven, as well as correspondence pertaining to legal and financial matters, travel and employment (including the New School for Social Research, Department of State, University of Massachusetts, Amherst).
  Arrangement
  Arranged chronologically.
  - Hans Speier, 1924-1938 (Box 1 (1-Biographical materials), Folder 1)
    German documents, including school certificates, etc.
  - Portrait sketch of H. Speier by N. Boyle, 1957 (Box 1 (1-Biographical materials), Folder 2)
  - Speier, Luise (Lisa) Griesbach, 1924-1933 (Box 1 (1-Biographical materials), Folder 3)
    German documents, including medical degrees.
  - Speier, Luise (Lisa) Griesbach, 1936-1938 (Box 1 (1-Biographical materials), Folder 4)
    American documents.
  - Speier, Lisa. Letters from Hans Speier, 1945-1946 (Box 1 (1-Biographical materials), Folder 5)
  - Speier, Lisa. Correspondence, primarily from Hans Speier, 1948-1954 (Box 1 (1-Biographical materials), Folder 6)
  - Family documents, predominately pertaining to Adolf Speier, father of Hans, 1936-1939; 1982 (Box 1 (1-Biographical materials), Folder 7)
  - Barton, Sybil (daughter of Hans). Correspondence, 1960-1984 (Box 1 (1-Biographical materials), Folder 8)
  - Speier, Steven W. (son of Hans). Correspondence, 1957-1981 (Box 1 (1-Biographical materials), Folder 9)
  - Speier, Anna. Correspondence, 1934 (Box 1 (1-Biographical materials), Folder 10)
  - Goldfarb, Samuel, attorney. Correspondence, 1966-1973 (Box 1 (1-Biographical materials), Folder 11)
  - "Jorf. Erzählung". Early typescripts of story by H. Speier, 1926 (Box 1 (1-Biographical materials), Folder 12)
  - "Die Transformation des Machtgedankens. Referat gehalten im Imperialismus-Seminar des Herrn Prof. Lederer und Dr. Mannheim". Text of an early lecture, 1927 (Box 1 (1-Biographical materials), Folder 13)
  - "The 17th of June 1953", Undated (Box 1 (1-Biographical materials), Folder 14)
    Tape of a radio broadcast, North-American Broadcasting Corporation.
  - Correspondence re: citizenship, 1939-1940 (Box 2 (1-Biographical materials), Folder 1)
  - New School for Social Research. Correspondence, 1941-1986 (Box 2 (1-Biographical materials), Folder 2)
  - Office of War Information. Personnel documents, correspondence, 1944 (Box 2 (1-Biographical materials), Folder 3)
  - Office of International Information and Cultural Affairs. Appointment papers, memoranda, correspondence, 1946-1947 (Box 2 (1-Biographical materials), Folder 4)
  - Department of State. Application and appointment papers, correspondence, 1944-1951 (Box 2 (1-Biographical materials), Folder 5)
  - The American University. Appointment letter, 1953 (Box 2 (1-Biographical materials), Folder 6)
  - University of Massachusetts, Amherst. Correspondence, 1968-1981 (Box 2 (1-Biographical materials), Folder 7)
  - Curriculum vitae, biographical sketches, Undated (Box 2 (1-Biographical materials), Folder 8)
  - Lists of publications, Undated (Box 2 (1-Biographical materials), Folder 9)
  - Read estate deeds, 1938; 1970 (Box 2 (1-Biographical materials), Folder 10)
  - Miscellaneous travel itineries, Undated (Box 2 (1-Biographical materials), Folder 11)
  - Miscellaneous conference schedules, Undated (Box 2 (1-Biographical materials), Folder 12)
  - Newspaper clippings about Speier, Undated (Box 2 (1-Biographical materials), Folder 13)
  - Membership directories, etc., Undated (Box 2 (1-Biographical materials), Folder 14)
  - Lists of book donations to University of Southern California, Los Angeles, 1969 (Box 2 (1-Biographical materials), Folder 15)
- Autobiographical writings, 1945-1989; 2; 25 file folders
  This series contains the autobiographical writings of Hans Speier and also includes transcripts of two interviews. Of particular interest are the typescripts of his published autobiography, From the Ashes of Disgrace: A Journal from Germany 1945-1955. The early versions of many of the typescript sections were taken from Speier's log notes for his trips to Germany for the Rand Corporation in the 1950s. (The complete log notes are located in Series 5: The Rand Corporation materials.).
  - "Myself". Personal statement prepared by Speier for the Rand Corporation files, 1954 March 23 (Box 2 (2-Autobiographical writings), Folder 16)
  - "Versuch einer Selbstzeichnung", Undated (Box 2 (2-Autobiographical writings), Folder 17)
  - "German Diary 1945-1955" (1945-1951). Early version of From the Ashes of Disgrace, Undated (Box 2 (2-Autobiographical writings), Folder 18)
  - "German Diary 1945-1955" (1952-1955). Early version of From the Ashes of Disgrace, Undated (Box 2 (2-Autobiographical writings), Folder 19)
  - From the Ashes of Disgrace, Undated (Box 2 (2-Autobiographical writings), Folder 18-20)
    Typescript with correspondence.
  - From the Ashes of Disgrace: A Journal from Germany 1945-1955. Part I, pp. 1-118, Undated (Box 2 (2-Autobiographical writings), Folder 21)
  - From the Ashes of Disgrace: A Journal from Germany 1945-1955. Parts II & III, pp. 118-238, Undated (Box 2 (2-Autobiographical writings), Folder 22)
  - From the Ashes of Disgrace: A Journal from Germany 1945-1955. Part III, pp. 239-349, Undated (Box 2 (2-Autobiographical writings), Folder 23)
  - From the Ashes of Disgrace: A Journal from Germany 1945-1955. Part IV, pp. 350-517, Undated (Box 2 (2-Autobiographical writings), Folder 24)
  - From the Ashes of Disgrace: "Berlin: Search -- Carl Hofer -- Chaos", Undated; typescript (Box 2 (2-Autobiographical writings), Folder 25)
  - From the Ashes of Disgrace: Introduction, Conclusion, Undated; typescript (Box 2 (2-Autobiographical writings), Folder 26)
  - From the Ashes of Disgrace, Undated; retyped sections (Box 2 (2-Autobiographical writings), Folder 27-28)
  - From the Ashes of Disgrace. Unused sections, Undated (Box 2 (2-Autobiographical writings), Folder 29)
  - "An Interview with Hans Speier". Transcript of interview by Michael Prinz, Undated (Box 2 (2-Autobiographical writings), Folder 30)
  - "Hans Speier. Gespraechsweise Mitteilungen zu einer intellektuellen Autobiographie". Transcript of interview by Ursula Ludz, 1982 October 4-1982 October 6 (Box 2 (2-Autobiographical writings), Folder 31)
  - "Hans Speier. Gespraechsweise Mitteilungen zu einer intellektuellen Autobiographie". Transcript of interview by Ursula Ludz, 1982 October 8; 1982 October 19-1982 October 20 (Box 2 (2-Autobiographical writings), Folder 32)
  - "Erinnerungen aus kleiner und grosser Zeit: fuer meine Kinder und jungen Freunde aus dem zwanzigsten Jahrhundert", Undated; photocopy of typescript (Box 2 (2-Autobiographical writings), Folder 33)
  - "'Die University in Exile' -- eine amerikanische Heimat fuer die deutsche Wissenschaft", 1984; typescript (Box 2 (2-Autobiographical writings), Folder 34)
  - "Autobiographische Notizen", ca. 1986 (Box 3 (2-Autobiographical writings), Folder 1)
    Typescript of introduction section of planned essay volume, The Truth in Hell and Other Essays.
  - "Autobiographische Notizen", ca. 1986; typescript (Box 3 (2-Autobiographical writings), Folder 2)
  - "Autobiographische Notizen", 1988; later typescript (Box 3 (2-Autobiographical writings), Folder 3)
  - "Autobiographical Notes". Early manuscript version of an English translation, Undated (Box 3 (2-Autobiographical writings), Folder 4)
  - "Autobiographical Notes", ca. 1989 (Box 3 (2-Autobiographical writings), Folder 5)
    Typescript of English translation.
  - The Truth in Hell and Other Essays (1989). Introduction: "Autobiographical Notes", Undated (Box 3 (2-Autobiographical writings), Folder 6)
    Typescript of table of contents, introduction.
- Correspondence files, 1911-1988; 3; 378 folders
  The correspondence files are arranged in four series, general correspondence with individuals A-Z; correspondence with publishers, newspaper editors, etc.; correspondence relating to the publication of the three volume series Communication and Propaganda in World History, and correspondence relating to the 1975 Thyssen Workshop "Probleme der Regierbarkeit".
  Arranged alphabetically.
  - Stationery (Hans Speier), Undated (Box 3 (3-Correspondence files), Folder 7)
  - A -- miscellaneous correspondence, Undated (Box 3 (3-Correspondence files), Folder 8)
  - Aebi, Andreas, 1974 (Box 3 (3-Correspondence files), Folder 9)
  - Albrecht, Richard, 1983-1984 (Box 3 (3-Correspondence files), Folder 10)
  - Almond, Gabriel A., 1946-1947; 1974-1980 (Box 3 (3-Correspondence files), Folder 11)
  - American Academy of Arts and Sciences, 1976 (Box 3 (3-Correspondence files), Folder 12)
  - American Association for Public Opinion Research, 1961 (Box 3 (3-Correspondence files), Folder 13)
  - Arrow, Kenneth J., 1978 (Box 3 (3-Correspondence files), Folder 14)
  - Arsenault, Theodore W., 1974 (Box 3 (3-Correspondence files), Folder 15)
  - Ascoli, Max, 1946-1957 (Box 3 (3-Correspondence files), Folder 16)
  - B -- miscellaneous correspondence, Undated (Box 3 (3-Correspondence files), Folder 17)
  - Bachmann, Siegfried, 1980 (Box 3 (3-Correspondence files), Folder 18)
  - Barbera, Henry, 1978-1979 (Box 3 (3-Correspondence files), Folder 19)
  - Barnes, Harry Elmer, 1943 (Box 3 (3-Correspondence files), Folder 20)
  - Baruch, Bernard M., 1939 (Box 3 (3-Correspondence files), Folder 21)
  - Beauffre, Général, 1966 (Box 3 (3-Correspondence files), Folder 22)
  - Bell, Aaron, 1953-1954 (Box 3 (3-Correspondence files), Folder 23)
  - Bendix, Reinhard, 1977-1981 (Box 3 (3-Correspondence files), Folder 24)
  - Benton, William, 1947 (Box 3 (3-Correspondence files), Folder 25)
  - Blumenthal, Fritz, 1984 (Box 3 (3-Correspondence files), Folder 26)
  - Boutell, Avis, 1987 (Box 3 (3-Correspondence files), Folder 27)
  - Brecht, Arnold, 1972; 1975 (Box 3 (3-Correspondence files), Folder 28)
  - Brill, Heinz, 1975 (Box 3 (3-Correspondence files), Folder 29)
  - Brodersen, Arvid, 1982-1984 (Box 3 (3-Correspondence files), Folder 30)
  - Brown, Frederick, 1944 (Box 3 (3-Correspondence files), Folder 31)
  - Brzezinski, Zbigniew, 1974 (Box 3 (3-Correspondence files), Folder 32)
  - C -- miscellaneous correspondence, Undated (Box 3 (3-Correspondence files), Folder 33)
  - Carroll, Wallace, 1982; Undated (Box 3 (3-Correspondence files), Folder 34)
  - Center for Advanced Study in the Behavioral Sciences, 1971; 1984-1985 (Box 3 (3-Correspondence files), Folder 35)
  - Clay, General Lucius, 1947 (Box 3 (3-Correspondence files), Folder 36)
  - Colm, Gerhard, 1947 (Box 3 (3-Correspondence files), Folder 37)
  - Columbia University Bicentenniel Broadcast Lectures (CBS), 1954 (Box 3 (3-Correspondence files), Folder 38)